## JETH WANJIKU MAINA CPA - K

**Address:** P.O. Box 4655 - 00100 Nairobi, **Cell:** +254 722 884053 **Email:** jethshiku@yahoo.com

### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

A transformational leader and a meticulous and credible professional who values integrity, I possess over 15 years of experience in various functions and roles namely Internal Audit, Risk management, Operations and Quality Management Systems. I have experience in the public sector dealing with health services and corporate sector in the financial services (working with insurance, asset management, SACCO), FMCG, Retail Electronic goods (Shipments, warehousing, operations & Reporting) education and research services.

Possess good understanding of business processes and internal control, incisive analytical/ thinking ability, excellent communication/ presentation and interpersonal skills and ability to provide insight and strategic input into the effective development and deliver outstanding internal audit reports, effective risk management processes, strong management and leading a team of five staff (directly) and 25 indirectly with favorable results, investigation and compliance related services to improve business performance and add value.

# **EDUCATION AND PROFESSIONAL QUALIFICATIONS**

# Masters of Business Administration (MBA) - Finance Option

*University of Nairobi* 

Sept 2006 - 4th Dec 2009

## Bachelor of Arts in Economics and Sociology - BA Economics & Sociology

Upper Second class – University of Nairobi

Sept 1996 – Dec 2000

### **Certified Public Accountant**

Vision Institute of Professionals & Pinnacle School of Business Registered member ICPAK: In good standing No.5249 Dec 2006

# **Leadership Program with Strathmore Business School**

Senior Management Leadership Program (SMLP 2017)

March 2017 - 1st Dec 2017

### Member - Women On Board Network (WOBN-K)

- WOBN - Corporate Governance Training

June 2019

2017

### Family Sacco & Housing Cooperative

Supervisory Committee – Chairperson

Effective March 2015 to date

### **Kenya Orient Insurance Pension Fund**

Sponsor appointed Trustee and Chairperson of the board of trustees

2014 to 2017

### **ICPAK Appointed Representative**

Banking & Related Financial Services Technical Committee at KEBS

2017

# Member of IRM (00038530), ISACA & IIA

**Pursuing CISA & IRM Certification** 

# **Board Of Management**

Kibutha Girls Secondary School Murang'a County

2019

### **WORK EXPERIENCE:**

# **Grimco Enterprise Limited**

**Managing Partner** Jan'2019 to date

# Nagoya Holdings Limited

Nagoya deals with shipment, warehousing and distribution of Sayona PPS brand state of the art home appliances and merchandise. Reporting Directly to the Board of Directors and the Consultant (Strategy & Operations).

# General Manager position & Financial Consultant **Key Responsibilities:**

Contract Based Aug – Dec'201

To provide leadership of critical operational and service delivery initiatives and optimise business and financial performance.

- Leadership Align processes, people and system in driving the operational and strategic goals.
- Managing daily operations Sales & Marketing, Finance and Reporting, Credit management, Logistics management, Audit & Risk Function, IT System, Administration and overall team management.

# **Kenya Orient Insurance Limited (KOIL)**

KOIL is licensed under the Insurance Act of Kenya and authorised to underwrite all classes of General Insurance Business.

Reported functionally to the Audit & Risk Board committee of the Board and Administratively to the Managing Director / CEO (in all the three roles).

# Head of Audit, Risk & Compliance

*April 2015 to June 2018* 

- **Key Responsibilities:** 
  - Management of the internal audit function Develop, implement 100% a risk-based audit plan and monitor the effectiveness of the internal control framework.
  - Develop and maintain an internal audit and risk strategy.
  - Risk management Review the risk management strategy and provide advice on the effectiveness of the framework and its implementation to senior management and audit committee.
    - Coordination and implementation of Enterprise Risk Management (ERM) Framework.
    - Monitoring major risks and embedding risks into the strategic planning process.
    - Facilitate in designing tools such appointing risk champions and trainings.
    - Designing and coordinating testing of a business continuity plan/disaster recovery.
  - Management of the Actuarial Function Spearheaded in setting up the actuarial control function:
    - Supported the entire organization with data analytics and trends on key performance indicators and assisted in designing of the daily monitoring tools.
    - Transitioned the staff through capacity development into the function.
  - Leadership and management role Enhanced leadership skills at Strathmore in the SMLP.
    - Supported management on the development and review of short-term and medium term strategic plans and goals.
    - Participated in hiring and training of competent staff, setting and reviewing staff performance targets in the department, coaching, mentoring and establishing staff training development needs.
  - ISO QMS 9001:2008 Played management representative role by coordinating all activities such as internal & external audits, management reviews, document review and control, championing of the quality management system and staff training.
  - Appointed and acted as the auditor of the subsidiary Alpha Africa Asset Management Company effective 1st March 2014.
  - Developed and managed the budget and cost management of the department.

### Achievement

Effectively led a team and executed 100% of the risk-based internal plan & risk management plan in 2014 & 2015 which led to level 3 risk maturity from level 1 and improved control environment.

- Contributed in staff development and mentorship and produced the employee of the year in 2015 in relation to annual performance as per the set KPIs.
- Spearheaded in the design of the Data Parts Solution process-flow and control framework for execution by the vendor Rolled out successfully in 2017.
- Recertification of the ISO 9001:2008 in 2016 based on maintained compliance with continual improvement noted by the certifying body.
- Committee member representing industry players at AKI representing Risk managers in vendor selection and evaluating development of a database platform tool that would facilitate in curbing claim fraud in the industry IMIDS that was rolled out 2<sup>nd</sup> January 2018 having began in 2016.

# Audit & Compliance Manager / Risk & Compliance Manager October 2011 to March 2015 Key Responsibilities:

- Risk management function Developed and implemented a Risk Management Strategy and Framework and compliance framework for the Company in line with the legal and regulatory requirements.
- Established risk management policies, procedures and standards across the company.
- Co-ordinated major risk identification, workshops and risk assessment and updated the Company's risks.
- Managed the internal audit function and responsibilities Made recommendations for internal processes improvements and monitored action plans for implementation.
- Provided trainings to staff at all levels on controls, risk management and strengthened the company's control environment.
- Collaborated with branch / regional underwriting staff to ensure loss control and revenue assurances considerations were accurately and appropriately administered within the underwriting decision making process to achieve Company's goals and objectives.

### Achievement

- Developed the standard operating procedures for Audit, Risk management and compliance functions.
- Designed company-wide staff incentive scheme in 2013 that contributed to the achievement of company goals over 100% of the set targets in 2014.
- Facilitated the documentation, testing of the controls and compliance in line with ISO 9001:2008 QMS and addressing all issues leading to the certification on 22<sup>nd</sup> April 2013.
- Awarded in contribution in developing a stand-alone mobile phone insurance product that was launched 2014 in the Insurance Industry.
- In 2012, unearthed contracted executed un-procedurally and saved the company Kes. 16.2Mn on retainer fees and recovered Kes. 600,000 on fraudulent receipts in 2013.
- Awarded the Department of the Year trophy in 2012, 2013 and 2014 and best staff in all the 3 years.
- Instrumental in driving operational efficiency and effectiveness where company revenue grew from Kes. 700m in 2010 Kes. 2.55bn in 2015.

### Senior Audit Executive

February 2011 to September 2011

### **Key Responsibilities:**

- Setting up the internal audit department in the company.
- Designed the internal audit framework policies and procedures, audit charter and annual plan.
- Carried out successful internal investigations.
- Developed audit programs and executed audit tests including management of sampling techniques.

#### Achievement

- Successful establishment of an effective and functional internal audit department.
- Designed internal audit framework plus an audit charter.
- Effectively set up and managed the Internal Audit Function.
- Unearthed fraud that led to reinforcement of ethical culture and reduction of staff related fraud.

3

# **National Hospital Insurance Fund (NHIF)**

NHIF is a Kenya government state corporation with a mandate to provide health insurance to Kenyans.

*Internal Auditor* - Reporting to the Internal Audit Manager **Kev Responsibilities:** 

June 2006 to Feb 2011

- **Internal audit tasks** Undertaking audit tests & procedures to determine the effectiveness and efficiency of financial systems, implementing annual audit work plans, appraising the internal controls to ensure effectiveness, enforcing compliance to policies and procedures, preparing comprehensive audit working papers and audit reports to ensure quality & standards are observed.
- Executing risk assessment to realize organisation objectives, established and maintained risk management processes as well as sensitization of staff at all levels on risk management.
- Carrying out investigations on suspected fraud and identifying trends.

### **Achievement:**

• Assisted through internal controls in curbing fraud on staff embezzlement of funds and hospital claims through vigilant surveillance and collaboration.

# National Hospital Insurance Fund (NHIF) Operations – Inspector / Compliance Officer Key Responsibilities:

December 2002 to May 2006

- Key tasks were; Enforcing 100% compliance with NHIF Act, client management, hospital accreditation, surveillance, member sensitization and registration.
- Handling branch operations and report writing.

### Achievement:

• Achieved 100% company and member registration and maintained zero debts accounts due to prompt follow-up.

### OTHER PAST EXPERIENCES

- Lecturing Intel College 2008 & 2009 (In Corporate finance, financial management and audit).
- Accountant Lymark Enterprises: January 2002 November 2002.
- **Data Clerk** International Research Network (IRN):

Aug 1998 – Dec 2001

### REFEREES

# Mr. David K. Kimani

**Chairman Audit & Risk Board Committee** 

Kenya Orient Insurance Limited P.O Box 34530 – 00100 Nairobi Tel: +254 722 656990

Mrs. Jackie Aduda

# Formerly Branch Manager

National Hospital Insurance Fund P.O Box 30443 – 00100 Nairobi

Tel: +254 720 127532

# Mrs. Thrity Engineer – Mbuthia

**Adjunct Faculty – Strathmore University** School of Management and Commerce

Email: tengineer@strathmore.edu

Tel: +254 737 700699